{"tossups": [{"question": "Like his former teammate Mark Messier <b>(MESS-ee-ay)</b> this man played for the New York Rangers towards the end of his career, with his last game coming in April 1999. This athlete influenced the style of play of the Edmonton Oilers dynasty of the 1980\u2019s, inspiring a more team-based strategy. When he retired, he was immediately inducted into the Hockey Hall of Fame, and the NHL retired his jersey, number 99, league-wide. For the point, name this hockey player, nicknamed \"The Great One.\u201d", "answer": "Wayne <b><u>Gretzky</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Spartan temple of the Bronze House was devoted to this deity, who was depicted in a gold-and-ivory <em>Parthenos</em> statue by Phidias. In the 550s BC, Pesistratus returned to power in Athens by constructing a golden chariot and hiring a \"tall woman\" to impersonate this deity. This deity was believed to have given olive trees to a city that was then named for her. For the point, name this Greek goddess of wisdom who was born from the head of Zeus.", "answer": "<b><u>Athena</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This ruler, who spared the life of his prisoner Guy of Lusignan, gave himself the upper hand and expelled his foes to a strip of coast in the Treaty of Ramla, to which he was a signatory. This man was victorious at the Horns of Hattin in 1187. This ethnically Kurdish leader lost at Arsuf to a charge led by the Knights Hospitallers. For the point, name this Sunni Muslim leader of the Ayyubid dynasty, who fought Richard the Lionheart in the Third Crusade.", "answer": "<b><u>Saladin</u></b> [or <b><u>Salah ad-Din</u></b> Yusuf ibn Ayyub]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A sculpture by this man, originally titled <em>The Vanquished,</em> was accused of having been cast from a live model. At the top of a larger sculpture by this man, three men lean forward with their left arms outstretched. This sculptor of <em>The Age of Bronze</em> depicted a scene from the Hundred Years War where six leaders of a French city surrender to Edward III with nooses hanging around their necks. For the point, name this French sculptor of <em>The Burghers of Calais</em> and <em>The</em> <em>Gates of Hell</em>.", "answer": "Auguste <b><u>Rodin</u></b> [Francois-Auguste-Rene <b><u>Rodin</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "James Dickey read \u201cA Strength of Fields\u201d at one of these events held in 1977. Another poem composed for an event of this kind opens \u201cthe land was ours before we were the land\u2019s.\u201d Robert Frost\u2019s \u201cThe Gift Outright\u201d and Maya Angelou\u2019s \u201cOn the Pulse of Morning\u201d are two notable poems written for, for the point, what kind of event, at which John F. Kennedy and Bill Clinton, respectively, heard poetry readings on their first day of office?", "answer": "Presidential <b><u>inauguration</u></b>s [or <b><u>inaugural</u></b>s]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This man and his royal counterpart began a series of railway attacks after capturing the port of Wejh. He shared his quarters with a boy named Dahoum, and declared his love for \"S.A.,\" who may have been another man, in the dedication for his autobiography <em>The Seven Pillars of</em> <em>Wisdom.</em> This man helped Prince Feisal's army take Aqaba during World War I, opposing Ottoman rule. For the point, name this British officer who helped liberate Arabia.", "answer": "Thomas Edward <b><u>Lawrence</u></b> [or T.E. <b><u>Lawrence</u></b>; or <b><u>Lawrence of Arabia</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Ralph Anspach instigated a long-running 1970s lawsuit after publishing a parody version of this game entitled \"Anti.\" This game may have been inspired by a Georgist propaganda tool created by Elizabeth Magie. It was put into its near-modern form by Charles Darrow, who used street names in Atlantic City for many of its elements, and all four of the railroads in this game are now defunct. For the point, identify this Parker Brothers board game in which the player can collect two hundred dollars for passing Go.", "answer": "<b><u>Monopoly</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man advocated for Virginia's right to reform clerical salaries from tobacco to cash in the Two Penny Act during the Parsons Cause. This man's writings about how \"Caesar had his Brutus, Charles I his Cromwell\" were suppressed by Francis Fauquier, and he followed his missives against the Stamp Act with another speech saying \"I know not what course others may take.\" For the point, name this Revolutionary War orator who said \"give me liberty or give me death.\u201d", "answer": "Patrick <b><u>Henry</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country used not-to-scale maps based on Buddhist cosmology until midway through its Chakri dynasty, which was preceded by the Ayutthaya kingdom. Anna Leonowens tutored the children of king Mongkut in this country, the only Southeast Asian power never to be formally colonized. For the point, name this country which nine kings of the regnal name Rama have ruled from Bangkok.", "answer": "<b><u>Thailand</u></b> [or <b><u>Siam</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This colony was earlier expanded after long-distance runners exploited an agreement to acquire as much land as a man could cover in three days. Also in this colony, several hundred Susquehannocks were killed by the Paxton Boys in the Conestoga Massacre. This colony is where <em>Poor Richard's Almanac</em> was published. For the point, name this colony founded as a Quaker refuge that later became the home of Benjamin Franklin in Philadelphia.", "answer": "<b><u>Pennsylvania</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "It's not Venice, but this city maintained a Temple of the Winged Lions. A narrow gorge called the <em>Siq</em> served as the entryway into this city, which Johann Ludwig Burckhardt rediscovered. This city used a water diversion system created by the Nabateans, who made it their capital while they were trading partners with imperial Rome, though that water has since dried up. This city's Great Treasury is a columned fa\u00e7ade carved into sandstone. For the point, name this ruin in Southern Jordan.", "answer": "<b><u>Petra</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This city was the origin of an urban legend about writing the word \"soul\" on shop windows. This city, which saw the 12th Street Riot, had mayors such as former NBA player Dave Bing and a man sent to jail after incriminating text messages came to light, Kwame (<b>KWAH-may</b>) Kilpatrick, This city was taken over by state-appointed manager Kevyn Orr after declaring bankruptcy in 2013. For the point, name this historic home of automakers in Michigan.", "answer": "<b><u>Detroit</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Yevgina Ginzburg describes entering a part of this system in Kolyma in the book <em>Journey</em> <em>Into the Whirlwind</em>. \u201cZeks\u201d were inhabitants of these places who often worked in gold mines or timber forests. Their population increased during the Great Purge of the 1930s and they were officially closed during the Khrushchev thaw in 1960. Alexander Solzhenitsyn compared this system to a chain of islands. For the point, name this system of Soviet prison camps.", "answer": "<b><u>Gulag</u></b> [or <b><u>labor camps</u></b> or <b><u>prison camps</u></b> until \u201cprison camps\u201d is said; or <b><u>lagerya</u></b> or <b><u>lagers</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person became famous fifty years after the similar Laura Bridgman. This co-founder of the ACLU is depicted on the Alabama state quarter. This person dedicated her autobiography to Alexander Graham Bell, though the text itself mostly praises the \"miracle worker\" Anne Sullivan, who first broke through by teaching her a sign for \"water.\" For the point, name this woman who became a prolific activist and author despite being blind and deaf since childhood.", "answer": "Helen Adams <b><u>Keller</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man once scammed visitors to an exhibit of curiosities by putting up a sign saying \"this way to the egress\" and then forcing those who left the building to buy another ticket. This man introduced the word \"jumbo\" into American English via the name of one of his elephants, and claimed \"there's a sucker born every minute.\" For the point, name this notorious showman of the 1900\u2019s whose namesake circus later partnered with Bailey and the Ringling Brothers.", "answer": "P.T. <b><u>Barnum</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man and his followers opposed the ideas of the established Cnidian school. The original Greek version of the Latin aphorism \u201cArs longa, vita brevis\u201d was attributed to this man, who lends his name to a \u201ccorpus\u201d that includes <em>On Airs, Waters, and Places</em> and <em>Prognostics</em>. The most famous text attributed to this man mentions a refusal to administer poisons and begins by swearing to Apollo and Asclepius. For the point, name this \u201cfather of western medicine\u201d, the namesake of an oath taken by doctors.", "answer": "<b><u>Hippocrates</u></b> of Cos", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, queen Eupraxia, or Adelaide, accused her husband of performing black masses. Matilda of Tuscany supported one side of this conflict, which was ended by the Concordat of Worms. During this conflict, a king was targeted by the Great Saxon Revolt. This controversy was briefly ended when Henry IV walked barefoot in the snow to Canossa Castle. For the point, name controversy over whether the pope or the emperor should appoint bishops.", "answer": "lay <b><u>investiture</u></b> controversy", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1968, this organization's research arm, the Guttmacher Institute, published the pamphlet <em>11 Million Teenagers</em>. This organization's leaders included Estelle Griswold, who was the plaintiff in the Supreme Court case that found a right to privacy. This organization was also the plaintiff in 1992's <em>Casey</em> decision about waiting periods and parental consent. For the point, name this organization founded by Margaret Sanger to offer birth control services.", "answer": "<b><u>Planned Parenthood</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A fictional version of this man shows up drunk to interrupt the proceedings in Plato\u2019s <em>Symposium</em>. He served as an adviser to the satrap Tissaphernes years after spurious charges of mutilating the <em>hermai</em> forced him to defect to Sparta, leaving him unable to command the Sicilian Expedition. For the point, name this Athenian statesman, a prominent commander during the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Alcibiades</u></b> (AL-sih-BYE-uh-deez)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Horace Schmahl defected from this man's defense team after a long-lost typewriter which Schmahl expected to vindicate this man turned out to be a crucial piece of evidence against him. This man, who helped negotiate the setup of the United Nations at the San Francisco Conference, was accused by Whittaker Chambers using the \"pumpkin papers.\" For the point, name this Soviet spy in the State Department whose 1948 espionage trial brought Richard Nixon to fame.", "answer": "Alger <b><u>Hiss</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler sent Robert Devereux to quash the rebellion of Hugh O\u2019Neill in Ireland. This monarch authorized the raid on Cadiz which was known as the Singeing of the King of Spain\u2019s Beard. She was celebrated as \u201cGloriana\u201d in Edmund Spenser\u2019s <em>The Faerie Queen</em>. This daughter of Anne Boleyn presided over the destruction of the Spanish Armada after succeeding her sister Mary I. For the point, name this daughter of Henry VIII who was known as \u201cThe Virgin Queen.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Elizabeth I</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Elizabeth</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This policy was vigorously opposed in one of the last public acts of Barry Goldwater, who claimed it had been ignored \"since at least the time of Julius Caesar.\" This policy was put into place to placate a faction led by Ike Skelton and originally included a \"don't pursue\" clause. This policy ended in a 2010 executive order from the Obama administration, seventeen years after Bill Clinton instituted it. For the point, name this compromise on military service by homosexuals.", "answer": "\"<b><u>Don\u2019t Ask, Don\u2019t Tell</u></b>\"[or more general answers such as \"the ban on <b><u>gays serving</u></b> <b><u>in the military</u></b>\" until \"Ike Skelton\" is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Three versions of this system are visible on the Behistun inscription near the city of Kermanshah. The Amarna letters were also made using this system, which was used to compose a list of <em>lugal,</em> or kings, such as Lugalbanda. Leonard Wooley dug up many financial texts made using it in the lost city of Ur. In this system, a reed stylus makes wedge-shaped markings in clay. For the point, name this writing system of the Sumerians, Assyrians, and other ancient Near East peoples.", "answer": "<b><u>cuneiform</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>writing</u></b> or <b><u>inscription</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This empire allowed local courts called <em>millet</em> for non-dominant religions under its secular <em>kanun</em> laws. A servant girl named Roxelana held much power in this empire, which the <em>Tanzimat</em> reforms modernized. This empire, which formally disbanded in 1923, recruited Balkan Christian boys for its elite janissary corps, and maintained the most famous harem. For the point, name this post-Seljuk Turkish sultanate ruled by Suleiman the Magnificent and founded by Osman.", "answer": "<b><u>Ottoman</u></b> empire [or <b><u>Osmaniyye</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1933, Robert Oschensfeld and Walther Meissner found that these materials expel magnetic fields. These materials were first discovered using James Dewar's techniques for cooling fluids, which Heike Kamerlingh Onnes applied. For the point, name these materials whose quantum mechanism was not fully explained until the development of BCS theory by John Bardeen in 1957, and are materials which have little or no electrical resistance.", "answer": "<b><u>superconductor</u></b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This city is home to David Rittenhouse's landmark orrery. In 1793, the Free African Society was asked to help fight a disastrous yellow fever epidemic in this city. This city's environs were the location of the battles of Brandywine and Germantown, which occurred after the flight of the Second Continental Congress from this city. For the point, name this 1790s capital of the U.S., where the Constitution and Declaration of Independence were drafted and signed.", "answer": "<b><u>Philadelphia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s bones were discovered buried under a latrine in his palace 17 years after his death from respiratory failure. This leader sent the Kagnew Battalion to the Korean War. This member of the Solomonic Dynasty was overthrown by a group of low-ranking military officials called the Derg, headed by Mengistu Haile Maram. For the point, name this last emperor of Ethiopia.", "answer": "<b><u>Haile Selassie</u></b> [<b>HIGH-ly suh-LASS-ee</b> but accept phonetically plausible answers; or <b><u>Ras Tafari</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city is also where Dr Pepper was invented. In response to later events in this city, a different city's Alfred Murrah Federal Building was attacked by Terry Nichols and Timothy McVeigh two years later. Janet Reno was blamed for a standoff with the Branch Davidians in this city. For the point, name this Texas city where federal agents burned David Koresh's compound in 1993 and where Baylor University\u2019s football team won many home games in 2014.", "answer": "<b><u>Waco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "October 2014 protests in this country ended a plan to implement a data tax on Internet traffic. It\u2019s not Russia, but controversy over the appointment of Colleen Bell, a soap opera producer, as U.S. ambassador to this country in 2014 led to an incident after John McCain described this country's prime minister as a \"neo-fascist dictator.\" For the point, name this country where the right-wing Fidesz (<b>FEE-dess</b>) party holds power under Viktor Orban in Central Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Hungary</u></b> [or <b><u>Magyarorszag</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In one nation, this action was done using Article 27 of the 1917 Constitution by Lazaro Cardenas. In another nation, this action led to a series of sanctions in the Abadan Crisis, and eventually to the implementation of Operation Ajax and the overthrow of Muhammad Mossadegh. Policies of this sort were enacted by Venezuela in 1976 and again in 2007, which led to lawsuits by ExxonMobil. For the point, name this economic action in which a government seizes control of privately-held petroleum reserves.", "answer": "<b><u>nationalization of oil</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Traditionally, this man is said to have taken the empty girdle of Mary back to the other Apostles after being the only witness to the Assumption. This man is held by the Nasrani community to have travelled to India and founded the Christian church there. An expression involving this Biblical character derives from his need to pole his finger into the nail marks on Jesus before believing in the Resurrection. For the point, name this Apostle who was called \"Doubting.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Thomas</u></b> [or <b><u>Didymus</u></b>]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A king of this name peacefully won control of the Holy Land from Al-Kamil in the Sixth Crusade and was known as \"stupor mundi.\" A king of this name called the Diet of Roncaglia to force his rule on the Lombard League, but was defeated at the Battle of Legnano. That emperor with this name drowned while swimming in full armor on his way to the Third Crusade. For the point, give this name of three Holy Roman Emperors, one of whom was called \"Barbarossa.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Frederick</u></b> [or <b><u>Frederick</u></b> I Barbarossa; or <b><u>Frederick</u></b> II]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man wrote the majority opinion in the <em>Olmstead v. U.S.</em> case, which ruled that the exclusionary rule did not generally apply to wiretaps. This former governor of the Philippines advocated \"dollar diplomacy\" through his Secretary of State, Philander Knox, and finished third in his re-election bid in 1912. For the point, name this Republican President, the only executive  to  become  a  Supreme  Court  justice  after  his  time  in  the  White  House.", "answer": "William Howard <b><u>Taft</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Some of these people wielded weapons they dubbed Enoch Hammers. They took their name from a possibly mythical apprentice named Ned, on whom they also jokingly blamed their actions. These people prompted the passage of the Frame-Breaking Act, as they frequently destroyed the mechanized looms and frames that put them out of work. For the point, name these vandalizing English workers who have lent their name to moderns who fear technology.", "answer": "<b><u>Luddites</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man led the Fida Group during a split of his political party, and opposed Muhammad Khan Junejo\u2019s faction. The Chagai-I and Chagai-II tests occurred under this man\u2019s regime. This man was exiled to Saudi Arabia after the Kargil War, when he was overthrown in a coup by Pervez Musharraf. For the point, name this leader of the Muslim League-N and current prime minister of Pakistan.", "answer": "Mian Muhammad Nawaz <b><u>Sharif</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One member of this family authored the bull <em>Exsurge Domine</em> as Pope Leo X. Another of its members was killed by an assassination plot orchestrated by the rival Pazzi family. Members of this family married both Henry II of France and Henry IV of France. Other members of this family were named Cosimo the Elder and Lorenzo the Magnificent. For the point, name this Italian family which patronized Michelangelo during their centuries long rule of Florence.", "answer": "<b><u>Medici</u></b> family", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During the trial resulting from this event, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court added stripes to his robe in imitation of Gilbert and Sullivan's <em>Iolanthe</em> (<b>EYE-oh-LAN-thee</b>). This event was \"floor-managed\" by Illinois Republican Henry Hyde, and it resulted from the Starr Report's accusations of perjury. For the point, name this 1998 to 1999 proceeding, after which the Senate a Senate voted against removing a Democratic President from office.", "answer": "<b><u>impeachment</u></b> of William Jefferson \"Bill\" <b><u>Clinton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This party included the office-seeking \"Hunkers\" as well as a group of abolitionists named for an aggressive method of catching rats, the Barnburners. Another faction of this party used matches to continue meeting after their lights were shut off and was called the Locofocos. This party also included the Albany Regency, which produced Martin van Buren. For the point, name this party in New York that affiliated with the national Jacksonian movement.", "answer": "New York <b><u>Democrat</u></b>ic Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s tutors included the Homeric scholar Alexander of Cotiaeum and the orator Fronto. Troops returning from a war with Parthia during this man\u2019s reign brought with them a wave of disease that became known as the Antonine Plague and claimed the life of his co-emperor Lucius Verus. While fighting the Quadi, he began writing a treatise inspired by the ideas of Epictetus. For the point, name this father of Commodus, an emperor who laid out his own Stoic philosophy in his <em>Meditations</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Marcus Aurelius</u></b> [prompt on partial answer]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man lamented the fact that Americans did not appreciate his large painting <em>Dying</em> <em>Hercules</em>, and he also included copies of thirty-eight earlier paintings in his own <em>Gallery of the</em> <em>Louvre</em>. This American painter also was inspired by his failure to say goodbye to his dying wife to invent a device which he inaugurated by sending a message to Baltimore reading \"What hath God wrought?\" For the point, name this inventor of the telegraph and a dot-dash code.", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Morse</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a painting by this man, a red-haired woman bites the neck of a man. A mourning woman assumed to be this artist\u2019s aunt kneels near the bed of his sister Sophie in his <em>The Sick Room</em>. The red background in a painting by this artist of <em>The Vampire</em> may have been inspired by his memories of the 1883 eruption of Krakatoa. In that painting, a man clasps his hands to his head while making the title noise. For the point, name this Norwegian artist of <em>The Scream</em>.", "answer": "Edvard <b><u>Munch</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Cicero mentions the only example of these people with a historically-attested name, a member of the Aedui named Diviciacus. Mythical examples of these people include Conchobar mac Nessa\u2019s attendant Cathbad. Julius Caesar claimed that these people sacrificed criminals by burning them inside a wooden effigy. Pliny the Elder describes a ritual in which they sacrificed white bulls after climbing oak trees to cut down mistletoe. For the point, name this class of Celtic people, most famous as priests.", "answer": "<b><u>druid</u></b>s [prompt on \u201c<b><u>Celt</u></b>ic <b><u>priest</u></b>s\u201d or equivalents; prompt on \u201c<b><u>Celt</u></b>s\u201d or \u201c<b><u>Gaul</u></b>s\u201d]", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "In the 1910\u2019s in this country, Clara Zetkin and Rosa Luxemburg advocated for socialism by distributing the Spartacus Letters. Communists in this country were violently opposed by paramilitary units called Freikorps. In 1923, Erich Ludendorff was briefly jailed after assisting in the Beer Hall Putsch in this country. For the point, name this country which suffered widespread hyperinflation and starvation while being ruled from Weimar just after World War I.", "answer": "<b><u>Germany</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An American ship seeking to aid a rebellion in this modern-day country was detained in the <em>Virginius</em> affair. This modern-day country was also the destination of the <em>Black Warrior</em>, as well as another ship which was taken over in a mutiny led by Cinque (<b>SEEN-kay</b>). This original destination of the <em>Amistad</em> was the subject of the Platt and Teller Amendments after the Spanish-American War. For the point, name this large Caribbean island.", "answer": "<b><u>Cuba</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 2013 Kevin Drum article examined data from multiple countries to show a correlation between this element and criminal behavior. This element was not completely banned from American gasoline until 1996, though it had been made illegal for use in house paints in 1978. This element is still used to make shielding aprons for X-ray patients. For the point, name this  element  which  can  inhibit  brain  development  when  ingested  by  children.", "answer": "<b><u>lead</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "With Venice, this city signed the Pactum Warmundi, and it was once controlled by Queen Melisende. This city was ruled by the leper king, Baldwin IV. A king of this city, Guy of Lusignan, was captured at the Battle of the Horns of Hattin. Pope Urban II called for the capture of this city at the Council of Clermont. For the point, name this city which became a kingdom after the First Crusade and is considered holy by several religions.", "answer": "<b><u>Jerusalem</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A year after successfully appearing on a Presidential ticket, Al Gore went on CNN to debate in favor of this bill. This agreement led to the resolution of longstanding disputes about truck inspection and softwood lumber subsidies. Brian Mulroney was instrumental in drafting this agreement, which Perot labeled the source of a \"giant sucking sound.\" For the point, name this pact championed by Bill Clinton which established a free trade zone with Canada and Mexico.", "answer": "<b><u>NAFTA</u></b> [<b><u>North American Free Trade Agreement</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "James Sovereign and John Hayes presided over this organization in its declining years, which were instigated when the Archbishop of Quebec condemned its largely Catholic membership due to its use of Masonic rituals. This organization's greatest success was the Wabash Railroad strike of 1885, and it was blamed for the Haymarket Square riot. For the point, name this skilled labor union founded by Uriah Stephens and led to its greatest size by Terence Powderly.", "answer": "<b><u>Knights of Labor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Bryan O'Neal gave a conflicting account of this man's death. This man was labeled an \"idiot\" in a controversial Ted Rall cartoon after his death, which is also the subject of the book <em>Where</em> <em>Men Win Glory</em>. Ralph Kayzlarich said that because this man was an atheist, his family should not be concerned about how he died. For the point, name this Army Ranger who died in Afghanistan after leaving a contract with the Arizona Cardinals following 9/11.", "answer": "Pat <b><u>Tillman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Prior to serving on the Supreme Court, Earl Warren was cross-nominated by the Republican and Democratic parties for this office. A chaotic 2003 recall election removed Gray Davis from this office. This office was held by a man nicknamed \"moonbeam\" in the 1970s, who returned to this office in 2011. For the point, name this elective office held nonconsecutively by Jerry Brown, who, in his current term, succeeded Arnold Schwarzenegger.", "answer": "<b><u>Governor of California</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After the Battle of Helsingborg, this group organized the Confederation of Cologne. Pirates called Likedeelers, or the Victual Brothers, attacked this group's cog ships. This organization built bases called kontors, one of which was the Steelyard in London. This organization forced the Treaty of Stralsund on Valdemar IV. The \"Jewel\" of this organization was the city of Lubeck. For the point, name this medieval alliance which dominated trade in the Baltic.", "answer": "<b><u>Hanseatic</u></b> League [or the <b><u>Hansa</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man briefly raised his daughter in his new \"air crib,\" which is often confused with a device designed to bombard animals with light, sound, and electrical shocks, his namesake \"box.\" This man, who trained pigeons to play table tennis, wrote against the existence of free will in his text <em>Walden Two</em>. For the point, name this disciple of John Watson and leading behaviorist psychologist, who experimented with operant conditioning.", "answer": "B.F. <b><u>Skinner</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "This man once evaded a term limits statute by concealing his wife Lurleen's cancer from her so that she would run for office in his stead. After his conversion to born-again Christianity, he renounced his prior campaigns and appointed two black officials to his cabinet. In 1963, he made the \"stand in the schoolhouse door\" to protest integration of his state's flagship university. For the point, name this segregationist governor of Alabama and 1968 Presidential candidate.", "answer": "George <b><u>Wallace</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One side was forced to withdraw from this war in the Treaty of Traventhal. The losing side ceded Ingria and Estonia in the Treaty of Nystad. Augustus the Strong entered this war to win Livonia for Poland. One side in this war was led by King Charles XII, who lost decisively at the Battle of Poltava. For the point, name this war in which Peter the Great and a Russian led coalition challenged Sweden\u2019s dominance over northern Europe in the early 18th century.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Northern</u></b> War [or <b><u>Second Northern War</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This resolution arose out of the DESOTO Patrols and was a confirmation of the temporary Operation Pierce Arrow. This bill was opposed only by Ernest Gruening of Alaska and Wayne Morse of Oregon. It was a response to reported attacked on the <em>Maddox</em> and <em>Turner Joy</em> in the namesake body of water. For the point, name this 1964 resolution which authorized Lyndon B. Johnson to escalate the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Gulf of Tonkin</u></b> Resolution", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The artificial Foy's Lake was created in this country in 1924, to serve a port on the Karanphuli (<b>KAH-ron-FOO-lee</b>) River that hosts a large tea auction. This country harbors nearly thirty thousand Burmese Rohingya (<b>row-HING-yuh</b>) refugees, who live in its city of Cox's Bazar. For the point, name this country that contains Chittagong (<b>CHIT-uh-gun</b>) and the \"Mouths of the Ganges\" (<b>GAN-jeez</b>), and fought a bloody war to establish independence from Pakistan in 1971.", "answer": "<b><u>Bangladesh</u></b> [People's Republic of <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>; or Gana Prajatantri <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This result was the subject of a quote claiming that the \"margin is too narrow to contain\" more information. In 1993, an attempt at proving this theorem was kept semi-secret when it was launched at the Isaac Newton institute; after a three-day presentation, the Taniyama-Shimura conjecture underlying this theorem was proclaimed proven by Andrew Wiles. For the point,  identify  this  long-unproven  theorem  about  the  exponents  of  three  integers.", "answer": "<b><u>Fermat's last</u></b> theorem", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This author had a habit of preparing daiquiris before watching agents of Che Guevara execute political prisoners each afternoon. This author, who included a prayer to \"nada\" in his short story \"A Clean, Well-Lighted Place,\" popularized a term for his contemporaries that Gertrude Stein applied to Americans serving in World War I. For the point, name this author of the \"Lost Generation\" who appended Stein's quote to his novel <em>The Sun Also Rises</em>", "answer": "Ernest <b><u>Hemingway</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man led the defeat of Tipu Sultan in the Third Mysore War, and he later secured the Peace of Amiens with France, as part of his successful latter career. Earlier, he had won the Battle of Camden against Horatio Gates but suffered a significant defeat when the comte de Grasse blockaded the James River and his army lost to Rochambeau and George Washington. For the point, name this British general who surrendered at Yorktown.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Cornwallis</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man defined the system of acceptable knowledge in each historical era as the \"episteme.\" He claimed that the \"medical gaze\" viewed a person's illness as separate from humanity in his <em>The Birth of the Clinic</em>. He used the story of a failed assassination attempt on Louis XV to open his history of prisons, <em>Discipline and Punish</em>. For the point, name this French historian of <em>The Order of Things</em> who theorized \"biopower.\"", "answer": "Michel <b><u>Foucault</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This man outsmarted Cornelius Vanderbilt and Daniel Drew to win the \"Erie War,\" a fight over shares in a railroad. He was suspected of bribing former Civil War general Daniel Butterfield in a scandal that also involved pressuring Abel Corbin to advise the President on commodity pricing. For the point, name this notorious \"robber baron\" who attempted to \"corner the gold market\" on Black Friday during the Grant Administration along with Jim Fisk.", "answer": "Jay <b><u>Gould</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, Henry Clay Work wrote about \"how the sweet potatoes even started from the ground,\" and a popular song by Patrick Gilmore looked forward to \"when Johnny comes marching home.\" \"Home Sweet Home\" was the most popular song for both sides in this war, for which \"Marching Through Georgia\" was composed. For the point, name this war in which opposing armies sang \"The Battle Hymn of the Republic\" and \"Dixie.\"", "answer": "American <b><u>Civil War</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man lost a million-dollar libel suit that he filed against <em>The National Review</em> for labeling him a \"fellow traveler\" with Communism, following his 1961 Nobel Peace Prize for advocating against nuclear tests. He had earlier won a Chemistry Nobel for his work on chemical bonds, during which he explained the concept of resonance. For the point, name this American \"father of molecular biology\" and only sole winner of two Nobels.", "answer": "Linus <b><u>Pauling</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2009, Charla Nash was attacked by one of these animals named Travis, leading to a controversial cartoon about the budget stimulus bill in the <em>New York Post</em>. These animals were studied at Gombe Stream in Tanzania by Jane Goodall, and many of them were retired to a sanctuary in Louisiana in 2013 after a phase-out of medical research on them. For the point, name these primates which are the closest living human relatives.", "answer": "<b><u>chimp</u></b>anzees", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "Hugh Dowding designed a telephone chain used by this organization to collect information about enemy positions. Its destruction was supposed to precede Operation Sea Lion. Members of it were nicknamed \u201cthe Few\u201d after a speech Winston Churchill gave praising them. An enemy shifted its strategy from bombing this group's bases to bombing civilian populations during the Blitz. For the point, name this air force that fought the Luftwaffe in the Battle of Britain.", "answer": "<b><u>Royal Air Force</u></b> [or <b><u>RAF</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Nicknames given to holders of this position include \"Dung-Named\" and \"Slit-nosed.\" A holder of this position won the Battle of Kleidion, after which he blinded most of the Bulgarian army. Members of the Comnenian dynasty held this position. A holder of this position was saved from the Nika riots by Belisarius and was advised by his wife, the former dancer Theodora. For the point, name this position held by Justinian, who ruled from Constantinople.", "answer": "<b><u>Byzantine emperor</u></b> [or anything indicating a ruler of the <b><u>Byzantine</u></b> empire or ruler of the <b><u>Eastern Roman</u></b> Empire; prompt on \"Roman emperor\" or \"emperor\"]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Along with Ronaldo and Lionel Messi, this player won the FIFA World Player of the Year title three times. In 2004, this man was named the best European footballer of the past 50 years by the UEFA Golden Jubilee Poll. This athlete played for Real Madrid, and won a World Cup on home soil in 1998. For the point, name this footballer who famously head-butted another player in the 2006 FIFA World Cup Final, which his team from France lost to Italy.", "answer": "Zinedine <b><u>Zidane</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A Neolithic site in this modern-day country with many sculpted bulls' heads on the walls is called \u00c7atal H\u00f6y\u00fck. Cilician pirates used the coast of this modern-day country as refuge. The Sultante of Rum covered much of this modern-day country, after the victors at Manzikert moved in to occupy much of it. The Seljuks were one group of this country's namesake ethnicity. For the point, name this country whose Asian landmass was previously called Anatolia or Asia Minor.", "answer": "<b><u>Turkey</u></b> [or <b><u>T\u00fcrkiye</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man's sons Gamal and Alaa were under trial for corruption at the same time in November 2014 that murder charges against this man were dropped. This man fell from power shortly after naming Omar Suleiman as his first-ever vice president. He was accused of complicity in 239 deaths in 2011 that occurred at Tahrir Square. For the point, name this former president of Egypt, who ruled from the 1981 assassination of Anwar Sadat until the \"Arab Spring.\"", "answer": "Hosni <b><u>Mubarak</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man posited a competition in which participants must guess who other participants will name the winner, known as his namesake \"beauty contest.\" This man, who was instrumental in setting up the Bretton Woods system after World War II, warned against the Treaty of Versailles in <em>The Economic Consequences of the Peace</em>. For the point, name this founder of post-classical economics who advocated deficit spending to avoid recessions.", "answer": "John Maynard <b><u>Keynes</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "A composer from this non-Finland country wrote the \"Gran Vals,\" which has become the \"most heard tune in the world\" thanks to its excerpting as the Nokia ringtone. A prominent ballet composer from this country created <em>Love, the Magician</em> and <em>The Three-Cornered Hat</em>. For the point, name this home of numerous classical guitar composers, such as Joaqu\u00edn Rodrigo (<b>wah-KEEN rah-DREE-go</b>) and Francisco T\u00e1rrega (<b>TAH-ray-gah</b>).", "answer": "<b><u>Spain</u></b> [Kingdom of <b><u>Spain</u></b>; or Reino de <b><u>Espana</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A conflict in this nation was partly analyzed by the Historical Clarification Commission, during which guerrillas were targeted by the Guns and Beans campaign of Efrain Rios Montt. Another leader of this nation passed Decree 900, which seized much of the holdings of the United Fruit Company. Rigoberta Menchu won a Nobel Prize for exposing the genocide of the Mayans in this country. For the point, name this nation whose leader Jacobo Arbenz was overthrown by the CIA.", "answer": "<b><u>Guatemala</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This song was originally composed for the review <em>Yip Yip Yaphank</em>, and it took its main melody from the humorous song \"When Mose with His Nose Leads the Band.\" It became the campaign song for the third term of Franklin Roosevelt, after it was debuted on radio on Armistice Day 1938 by Kate Smith. For the point, name this Irving Berlin song which says \"stand beside her and guide her\" about the \"land that I love,\" often during the seventh inning of baseball games.", "answer": "\"<b><u>God Bless America</u></b>\"", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This colony is described in the book<em> Mourt's Relation</em> and was originally led by John Carver. Miles Standish was a military commander in this colony, which was long governed by Edward Winslow and William Bradford. This colony was advised on how to plan corn by Squanto and arranged a feast with Massasoit (<b>MAH-suh-SOY-it</b>) that is often called the origin of Thanksgiving. For the point, name this colony settled by the <em>Mayflower</em> Pilgrims.", "answer": "<b><u>Plymouth</u></b> Colony (do NOT accept Massachusetts or Massachusetts Bay)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The expression \"your name is mud\" may derive from a doctor implicated in this event, Samuel Mudd. Mary Surratt became the first woman executed by the federal government as a result of this event, which only injured secondary target William Seward. This event interrupted the play <em>Our American Cousin</em> and was perpetrated by an actor who shouted \"sic semper tyrannis.\" For the point, identify this April 1865 murder by John Wilkes Booth.", "answer": "<b><u>assassination</u></b> of Abraham <b><u>Lincoln</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}